<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Eventually Consistent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jdgoldie.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jdgoldie.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-10T14:47:47+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jdgoldie.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joshua Goldie]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reliable Delivery in Akka and Number 9]]></title>
    <link href="http://jdgoldie.github.io/blog/2015/01/07/reliable-delivery-in-akka-and-number-9/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-07T20:29:58+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jdgoldie.github.io/blog/2015/01/07/reliable-delivery-in-akka-and-number-9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week <a href="https://vaughnvernon.co/?page_id=178">Vaughn Vernon</a> teased/announced <a href="https://vaughnvernon.co/?p=976">Number 9</a> which he proposes as an alternative to Akka&rsquo;s AtLeastOnceDelivery.  One interesting difference
is the use of the Message Journal to store unconfirmed messages.  This design is a siginificant departure from Akka&rsquo;s AtLeastOnceDelivery.</p>

<blockquote><p>You see, AtLeastOnceDelivery doesn’t by default support message persistent storage, and actually only
offers any resemblance to it when your actor is given a chance to store a snapshot of its current state.
Since a snapshot is not offered for every message you send via AtLeastOnceDelivery, a crash could easily
render any number of messages undelivered.</p></blockquote>

<p>Since snapshots are <em>optional</em> and in most cases <em>periodic</em> based on either message throughput or elapsed time, you should
count on losing messages at some point.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>In addition to being responsible for keeping track of unconfirmed messages, AtLeastOnceDelivery also makes each Entity responsible for attempting redelivery of
its own messages and tracking delivery confirmations.  <em>Number 9</em> moves the redelivery task to a separate actor named Redeliverer.  This is an interesing idea
that appears to fix one issue I&rsquo;ve encountered with AtLeastOnceDelivery and its use of the <em>redeliveryTick</em>.</p>

<p>Each actor using AtLeastOnceDelivery sets up a redeliveryTick system timer to trigger a check for unconfirmed messages.  This timer fires even when the actor has no
unconfirmed messages.  The tick has the side effect of making receiveTimeout unusable.  On a recent project that used the cluster sharding extension with passivation support,
this conflict prevented actors from passivating correctly.  Actors using AtLeastOnceDelivery with <em>no</em> unconfirmed messages would refuse to passivate as long as they
were receiving the redeliveryTick.</p>

<p>The Redeliverer looks to move this functionality out of the entities which should allow sharding/passivation to work as designed.</p>

<p>While making these departures from the current implementation, it&rsquo;s important to remember that <em>Number 9</em> is an alternative implementation of at-least-once.</p>

<blockquote><p>Since Number 9 provides an at-least-once delivery mechanism, you will likely want to take whatever design steps are necessary to make the
[the processor] an Idempotent Receiver. This requirement will be more or less challenging depending on the state machine needed by the actor.</p></blockquote>

<p>Because exactly-once <a href="http://brooker.co.za/blog/2014/11/15/exactly-once.html">is not what you want</a>.</p>

<p>From what&rsquo;s been shared so far <em>Number 9</em> sounds like a good approach to fixing some of the issues with AtLeastOnceDelivery.  The only drawback I see at this point
is that it&rsquo;s unreleased and I&rsquo;d really love to take a look at the code.  I&rsquo;ll be watching this tool for future articles and releases.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Queues Don't Fix Overload]]></title>
    <link href="http://jdgoldie.github.io/blog/2014/12/12/queues-dont-fix-overload/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-12T17:00:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jdgoldie.github.io/blog/2014/12/12/queues-dont-fix-overload</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really enjoyed <a href="https://twitter.com/mononcqc/">Fred Hebert</a>&rsquo;s great <a href="http://ferd.ca/queues-don-t-fix-overload.html">post</a> on queues and system overload.  An overflowing sink is my favorite image of what happens to your
system when a queue is used as a buffer to mask the slow parts of the system.</p>

<p><span class="caption-wrapper left" style="width: 426px"><img class="caption" src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/proxy/-trPHfKNxS07bxGXx8qTSaELzrkz-6sPmZ-DGtLhKWbcKPfvK9Wr5zscdk9yLftXT9iBtkR3YWscwmyiunRT152o8gsOCrp9SrivK7EcPXozSd2uI679U1OAgMD1vFo=w426-h295"  alt="Image Credit: Fred Hebert"><span class="caption-text">Image Credit: Fred Hebert</span></span></p>

<p><span class='pullquote-left' data-pullquote='It becomes a kind of bucket list for your application'>
Systems have limits.  No matter how much we, as developers and architects, like to throw around derivations of the word
<em>scalable</em> in design discussions, the limits are there.  And you are going to hit them.  Dropping in a queue to buffer
requests only hides the fact that there is a limit.  It becomes a kind of bucket list for your application &ndash; work you are hoping
it will complete before it crashes or reaches the next maintenance or upgrade window.  And then, the queue has made the
problem worse, even if you made it persistent.
</span></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Fred&rsquo;s suggestion, with which I completely agree, is to use back-pressure mechanisms so the system gracefully handles
new user requests as it approaches its operational limits.</p>

<blockquote><p>But someone should have picked what had to give: do you stop people from inputting stuff in the system,
or do you shed load. Those are inescapable choices, where inaction leads to system failure.</p>

<p>And you know what&rsquo;s cool? If you identify these bottlenecks you have for real in your system, and you put
them behind proper back-pressure mechanisms, your system won&rsquo;t even have the right to become slow.</p></blockquote>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='No feedback at all is worse that telling the user that the system is busy.'>
Notice that this only keeps your system from becoming slow and falling over on itself.  It <em>does not</em> guarantee that all
user requests will be served, merely that they will be handled.  This may sound like splitting hairs, but telling the
user that the system is too busy to handle their request is better than failing to respond before reaching either the HTTP tineout
or the limit of their patience.  No feedback at all is worse that telling the user that the system is busy.
</span></p>

<p>Back-pressure mechanisms, both formal and informal, exist all around us:</p>

<ul>
<li>A theme park stops letting riders enqueue for a <a href="https://www.universalorlando.com/Rides/Universal-Studios-Florida/Harry-Potter-And-The-Escape-From-Gringotts.aspx">popular attraction</a> if they cannot get through the ride before the park closes</li>
<li>A cell-phone sends a new caller to voice-mail if a call is already in progress</li>
<li>A line outside a restaurant signals a potential diner to seek other options</li>
</ul>


<p><span class="caption-wrapper center" style="width: 500px"><img class="caption" src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3765/9501576373_1c159d36f1.jpg" width="500" height="367"  alt="Image Credit: [Corey Seeman][5]"><span class="caption-text">Image Credit: <a href="https://flic.kr/p/ftC4Ci">Corey Seeman</a></span></span></p>

<p>It may seem strange, perhaps even wrong to plan to refuse a user request, but it actually provides a better experience than trying
to take on more work than the system can handle.  Imagine if the theme park didn&rsquo;t close the line until the park closed, and at that point,
everyone still waiting had to leave.  Those riders would have a worse experience than being turned away from the line in the first
place.  They go away disappointed instead of angry and they come back earlier the following day.</p>

<blockquote><p>To make stuff usable, a proper idempotent API with end-to-end principles in mind will make it so these instances of
back-pressure and load shedding should rarely be a problem for your callers, because they can safely retry requests and know if they worked.</p></blockquote>

<p>I recently encountered a failure in an online ticketing system.  I was purchasing tickets to the Nutcracker Ballet, and after debating the merits
of orchestra-rear versus first-balcony seats, I was ready to checkout.  Three pretty good seats were in the cart, parking was reserved,
credit card information was entered.  I hit <em>Complete Purchase</em>.  I watched the spinner until the request timed out.</p>

<p>Did I get the seats?  Had my credit card been charged?  How long should I wait for a confirmation email before assuming the purchase
had not gone through?  I tried again with the same result.  I tried again.   The ticketing system was
now completely unresponsive.  Did I have six tickets to the ballet?  I wrestled with this and other questions
as I tried to get to sleep that night.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='I don&#8217;t have to be a UX guy to know that&#8217;s a horrible user experience.'>
I checked the next morning and saw that the first set of seats I had attempted to purchase were still showing as available.  That meant
my purchases had failed.  I don&rsquo;t have to be a UX guy to know that&rsquo;s a horrible user experience.  The system should either refuse to let me
start the ticket selection process or prevent me from completing checkout if it&rsquo;s under too much load.  Either one is a better choice than
letting the HTTP request timeout.  It&rsquo;s the difference between making your system looking busy and looking broken.
</span></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
